《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《大难临头》
啊 啊
Ah, ah,
那可真是…
that was…
狂野啊
vigorous.
这点体力活 对你来说
You look like the sort of man
似乎是小意思嘛
that could handle it.
我喘得厉害呢…
I am rather rugged…
我得走了
Must go.
爸爸会担心的
Father will be worried.
他是该担心了…
As well he should be…
我得走了
I have to go.
如果你要走 我会心碎的
If you do, my heart will break.
求我留下来啊
Ask me to stay.
留下吧
Stay.
求我
Ask me.
叫我的名字
By my name.
你连我叫什么 都不知道吧？
You do not even know it, do you?
叫Sura
Sura.
我叫Sura
My name is Sura.
Sura啊
Sura.
名字跟你的人一样美
As beautiful as the woman herself.
我叫…
My name is…
是女人都知道你的名字
Every woman knows who you are.
见你就躲
And to avoid you.
我有这么可怕么？
That bad, am I?
哈 可怕极了
Huh, the worst.
那你为何跟声名狼藉的男人 共度春宵呢？
Then why lay with a man of such ill reputation?
天神让我来的
The gods led me to your bed.
天神？
The gods?
他们显灵了
They come to me.
在我梦中显灵
In my dreams.
他们告诉我 你会成为什么样的人
They showed me the man you could become.
成为？
Could?
前提是走对了路的话
If set upon the right path.
关于我的未来
And what else did the gods tell you
天神都告诉你什么了？
about my future?
你绝不会移情别恋
That you will never love another woman.
心情沉重
The heart weighs heavy.
期盼团圆
So much hope in reunion.
却不得善终…
To come to such bitter end…
怎么会这样？
How is it so?
是我的错
The fault is mine.
那不勒斯的回程路 是出了名的危险
The road from Neapolis is known to be treacherous.
我应该派双倍人马护送
I should have doubled the guard.
三倍才对
Tripled it.
我应该晚点放Barca自由
I should have delayed giving Barca his freedom
派他去行使护卫之责
and sent him along as well.
愿天神恕罪
Pray the gods forgive my error.
不
No.
你兑现了诺言
You kept your word.
错在取她性命之人
The fault lies with the men who took her life.
错在Claudius Glaber
And with Claudius Glaber,
是他将她判为奴籍
who condemned her to slavery.
事已至此
There is nothing to be done
回天无力
to change what has passed.
我们必须着眼未来
We must look towards the future.
你是送雨的使者
You are the Bringer of Rain.
屠灭死亡之影的勇士
The Slayer of Death.
让我们携手 将斯巴达克斯这名字
Together we will etch the name Spartacus
载入史册
to the pillars of history.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
她不是这么叫我的
That is not what she called me.
这不是我的名字
That is not my name.
现在是了
It is now.
近一年来 你让我到处找寻
Nearly a year you had me searching
这个色雷斯女人
for that Thracian woman.
为什么让我暗地里杀死她？
Why have me take her life short of the mark?
不得已而为之
An unfortunate necessity.
这些钱够了吧？
I trust the sum sufficient?
如果还有其它「不得已」
If other "necessities" arise,
千万记得找我
consider me your man.
花这么多钱把她找回来 却是死人一个
So great an expense, to have her delivered all but dead.
你还不如告诉斯巴达克斯
You could just as easily have told Spartacus
她客死异乡了
that she perished abroad.
她是他的命根子
She was his life.
是他的心肝宝贝儿
The heart beating beneath his chest.
所以不能这么说
No.
这种男人不会轻易相信她死了
Such a man would not believe she was gone,
除非他亲眼看见
unless his own eyes told him it was so.
这是唯一的办法
It was the only course.
你早该告诉我
And one which you could have told me
你的打算
you were undertaking.
我说过 不会让鲜血玷污
I would keep such blood from these hands,
你的玉手
as I have said.
我的手握着你的手
They hold yours.
难道不会间接沾染到么？
Are they not stained by the touch?
最近死了太多的人
There has been too much death of late.
我要冒险一试
I would turn towards more respectable ventures.
心无所念的斯巴达克斯
With his wife removed from thought,
将被我锻造成
I will mold Spartacus into a gladiator
史上最伟大的角斗士
the likes of which the world has never seen.
他已经战胜了Theokoles
He has already defeated Theokoles.
想想看 心无旁骛 只为胜利而战
Imagine what he will accomplish once his mind
他将锐不可当
has been focused on nothing but victory.
而你将成为 共和国最富有的
You will be the greatest lanista
角斗商
in the Republic.
由此 我们将
And on such a title we will climb
声名远播
beyond our station.
名扬全国
Beyond Capua.
也许还能跻身议院
Perhaps to the very steps of the Senate itself.
他还在发烧？
The fever still grips him?
如果情况好转 记得通知我
I would know if his condition changes.
我有话跟你说 Doctore
A word, Doctore.
Pietros 说吧
Pietros.
那些鸟 Barca房中的那些
The birds, left in Barca's cell.
我应该怎么处理它们呢？
What should I do with them?
随你便
Whatever you wish.
他曾说 我们赎身之日
He said we would release them,
便是它们自由之时
once he gained our freedom.
他还打算为你赎身？
He intended yours as well?
就是为这 他才去和主人谈赎身
That was his purpose in speaking with our Dominus.
Ashur说 两个人的自由 要价太高
Ashur said the price was too steep for us both.
Ashur说？
Ashur?
他帮我们说情来着
He helped negotiate the sum.
我接着养 行吗？
Would it be OK if I kept them?
我是说那些鸟？
The birds?
没人会在意的
It would not cause notice.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这可不明智
That is unwise.
如果守卫发现你有把匕首…
If the guards were to see you with it…
我已受尽折磨
What could they do to me,
他们还能想出什么新花样？
that hasn't already been done?
我不该离开她
I never should have left her.
不是你离开了她
You did not leave her.
而是他们抢走了她
She was taken from you.
在我参战前
Before I left for war,
她曾求我留下
she asked me not to go.
你参战也是为了
You did what you thought was right.
保护她
To protect her.
趁早把这匕首扔下悬崖
You should toss that over the cliff.
别干傻事
Best to be done with such thoughts.
小心点 这东西比你还值钱
Careful with that. It costs more than your worth.
家族复兴 指日可待了
It won't be long until our house is finally livable again.
眼光放长远些！
Tilt your bow higher!
我们意在天下！
We aim at the heavens!
建造Batiaus皇宫！
The Palace of Batiatus!
让达官显贵趋之若鹜
Where dignitaries kneel
只为一窥我的财富！
to suck the cock of my good fortune!
嗯 他们可得排队…
Well, they'll have to get in line…
Crixus怎么了？
Crixus?
躺着别动！
Lie still!
最好遵医嘱
Best to heed the advice.
我们一度以为你必死无疑
For a while we thought you for the afterlife,
我何时能再战？
When will I fight again?
他问 何时能再战
When will I fight again he says.
只管好生养病
Worry of nothing but recovery,
有朝一日 民众会再度为你癫狂
the crowd will once again cheer the name Crixus.
过来说句话
A word.
我不方便
It would be improper for me to visit
去训练场看你
you in the ludus.
但我的心时刻牵挂着你
But know that my thoughts are with you.
我会吩咐女仆Naevia 帮忙打点你的生活
I'll send my slave Naevia often to attend your needs.
好好休息
Rest now,
什么也不要担心
and worry for nothing.
你的练习剑 战神
Your swords for practice, Champion.
训练开始了
The day's training begins.
捉对厮杀！
Pair up!
换剑和盾来！
Sword and shield!
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
跟我对阵
You face me.
你妻子过世了
Your wife's passing.
我感到非常遗憾
That was an unfortunate thing.
还有你夭折的逃跑计划
As was your plan for escape.
虽然 我多年滴酒未沾
I have not tasted wine for many years.
但还不至于被一杯酒灌醉
Yet a single cup would not rob me of my senses.
我只想让你睡着…
The choice was to see you sleep…
或不再醒来？
Or never awaken?
你的企图未被察觉
Your victory over Theokoles
只是因为Batiatus还沉浸于
is the only reason Batiatus
你屠灭Theokoles的胜利之中
does not know of your treachery.
否则战神的身份 也救不了你
Champion or no, you would be crucified.
那就省省口舌 等着看吧！
Then part your lips and see it done!
下次再想逃…
Next time you seek escape…
最好先杀了我
you'd best kill me.
一半就好 嗯？
Make it half, yeah?
Mercato啊！
Good Mercato!
乱糟糟的 你别介意啊！
You must excuse the chaos!
本想在你来以前
I had hoped to see such affairs
把事情完工的
completed before your arrival.
财运亨通啊
Fortune favors you.
自从卡普亚喜降甘霖后 人人如此！
As it does all of Capua, since the rains!
我时间紧迫
My time is pressed.
来 我们切入正题
Come, let us to business.
哦 谈正事吧
Ah, to the matter then.
为彰显我家族的荣耀 我要举办竞技赛
I secured six of your men for my games,
并已和你敲定你手下六人参赛的事
honoring the storied history of my family.
若你还记得的话 这一切均已于火神节前安排妥当
Arrangements made before the Vulcanalia, if you recall.
恍然如昨啊
As if it were yesterday.
嗯 我已决定
Well, I've decided as highlight
要重现罗马大胜梅迪的辉煌战史
to reenact Rome's victory over the Maedi,
这么个色雷斯蛮族部落 竟然胆敢侵犯马其顿
the Thracian tribe who dared invade Macedonia.
他们如此傲慢无礼
They were slaughtered for their insolence
早已被我祖父
by my grandfather,
Marcus Minucius Rufus屠戮殆尽
Marcus Minucius Rufus.
他的确声名显赫 万古流芳！
A name that carries weight, long after it's passing!
我打算重现他的辉煌
I'd planned for to play the very man himself,
横扫千军
leading the charge.
抱歉
Apologies.
Crixus尚未从Theokoles一战中
Crixus is yet recovering
恢复元气
from his battle with Theokoles.
哦 不出所料
Ah. As I suspected.
换Gnaeus怎样？
Perhaps Gnaeus, then?
我倒倾向于 派斯巴达克斯出场
I turn thought towards Spartacus.
他的身价可不一般呢
He is much in demand.
要多少钱？
The cost of such a thing?
再多加40%
An additional forty percent.
包括派犯人去扮演色雷斯人的角色？
Prisoners to play the Thracians included?
包在我身上
Consider it done.
我要让卡普亚城人尽皆知！
I will see it announced all over Capua!
斯巴达克斯 「死亡之影」的屠灭者！
Spartacus, Slayer of Theokoles!
演绎我祖父的辉煌！
To assume the mantle of my grandfather!
伟大的一天！
A great day!
Pietros啊
Pietros.
多拿点水来
Bring more water.
快去
Now.
蠢货
Fucking pig.
看他把爪子搭在人家身上那邪样…
The way he paws at the boy…
这一切都怪Barca
The fault lies with Barca.
舍他而去
For leaving him.
送出了吗？
Is it delivered?
说到做到
As promised.
是给我妻子的信
A letter to my wife.
真难得啊
Long overdue.
是啊
Yeah.
有她的回信吗？
Did you bring reply?
她不要我转达
She did not favor me with one.
坚持亲自答复
She insisted on bringing you message herself.
你是怎么进来的？
How did you gain entry?
你的人Ashur代我向Batiatus乞求
Your man Ashur spoke to Batiatus on my behalf.
他为此问你要钱了？
Did he ask coin for the service?
他说他会找你商量
He said he would take the matter up with you.
现下谁还在意钱财 嗯？
Who cares of coin on such a day, eh?
这孩子长这么大了！
The boy has grown monstrous!
他的母亲也愈发美丽了啊…
And his mother ever more beautiful…
我想念你唇齿间的味道
I miss the taste of your lips.
那封信令我深感意外
The letter came as a surprise.
我每日祈求获知 有关你的些许消息
Every day I prayed for word.
祈祷消息传来时
And that it would not be news
不是关于你战死竞技场
of your death in the arena.
我们说过不通信的 Aurelia
We agreed no letters, Aurelia.
为了使你和孩子远离血海
To keep you and the boy far from this.
不要忧心我的事
And my mind on the task.
是什么使你有所改变呢？
And what has changed?
一个朋友
A friend.
他所失去的一切
His loss.
一个朋友
A friend.
你因一个朋友而改变主意
You are moved by a friend.
我因想见妻子的渴望 而改变主意
I am moved by the need to see my wife.
为了确信她真实可寻
To know she is still real,
并非痴人说梦
and not the dream of a desperate man.
再过一年多 我的债务即可还清
After one more year my debts will be paid.
我们便可重新开始
We can start again.
一家团聚
All of us, together.
我们现在就走吧
We should have just left.
去庞贝城 或西西里岛
To Pompeii. Or Sicilia.
这么做有损荣耀
It would not have been honorable.
荣耀？
Honor?
当你欠下巨额赌债 又无力偿还时 荣耀何在？
Where is the honor in debts of gambling and chance?
当你抛离妻儿时 荣耀何在？
Where is the honor in leaving your wife and child?
我所犯下的每一个错误…
Every mistake I have made…
我都会尽力矫正
I will set right.
我会成为配得上你的男人
I will be the man you deserve.
自此刻起 我的命便是你的
From this moment on my life is yours,
唯你专属
and yours alone.
我怀上了
I am with child.
怀上了？
Child?
你什么意思？
What is your meaning?
Varro啊…
Varro…
告诉我
Your meaning.
自你走后 生活困苦不堪
Your absence has been difficult.
你给的钱仅够
The money you send barely enough
勉强糊口
to keep us fed and sheltered.
是Titus提供了帮助
Titus offered assistance.
Titus是谁？
Titus?
集市上认识的熟人
An acquaintance, from the marketplace.
你为了回报他的施舍 就把身子给卖了？！
And you repay him by spreading your fucking legs?!
不是的 我本来仅仅将他视作朋友
No. I thought of him only as a friend.
是他强行占取我的身子
He forced himself upon me.
你为什么不阻止他？
Why didn't you stop him?
你以为我想这样吗？
You think I wanted this?
我被人肆意糟践时 你在哪儿 Varro？
Where were you, Varro?
那时你在哪儿？
Where the fuck were you?
我在拼命
Fighting.
为了我们而拼命
For us.
就像你本该做到的一样
As you should have been.
Batiatus家族 旗下勇士无数
The House of Batiatus is filled with champions.
我父亲如此
Father's.
我祖父亦如此
Grandfather's.
不久你也会成为他们中的一员
Soon you will stand among them.
我要让你名垂青史
I have commissioned you to be immortalized in stone,
哪怕不惜一切代价
at great expense.
我很荣幸 主人
You honor me, Dominus.
荣誉将不再只属于他们
Well the laurels do not cease there.
Mercato坚持
Good Mercato has insisted that
让斯巴达克斯在他的比赛里当前锋！
Spartacus be moved to the forefront of his games!
你将扮演他传说中的祖父
You will take the guise of his storied grandfather,
即Marcus Minucius Rufus！
Marcus Minucius Rufus!
Rufus吗？
Rufus?
你知道他？
You know of him?
我听说过这个名字
I have heard the name,
小时候听父亲提到过
spoken by my father when I was a boy.
你将会穿上他的战袍
You will be dressed in his very armor,
我们还有四个角斗士将扮成罗马军团
four of our gladiators bedecked as Roman Legion.
那我们的敌人呢？
Our enemy?
六个死囚
Six prisoners sentenced to execution,
将打扮成色雷斯梅迪部落
clad in the barbaric fashion
典型的野蛮人！
of the Thracian hordes of the Maedi!
有你驾驭全场
It will be a grand spectacle,
那场面该多么恢弘壮阔啊！
with you its shining helm!
我不会上场的
I will not fight.
你误会了
You misunderstand.
我不是在请示你
I do not ask.
我是在命令你
I command.
我不会打扮成一个罗马人
I will not dress as a Roman
并假装屠杀我的同胞
and pretend to slaughter my own people.
是时候放开你那执着的过去了
It is time for you to release your hold upon past.
你不再是色雷斯人
You are no longer of Thrace.
你命中注定
You are destined for great
要成就一番大业 斯巴达克斯
and wonderful things, Spartacus.
接受天神赐予你的成功之路吧
Embrace the path the gods have set you upon.
你的心被太多的悲痛所蒙蔽
Your mind is clouded by grief.
好好想清楚
Pause to clear it.
你就像在给孩子擦洗
You bathe me as if a child.
你必须休息
You must rest.
躺好别动
Lay still.
你会让伤口裂开的
You'll reopen your wounds.
我甚至都起不了身
I can't even rise.
迟早会的
In time.
伤痛总是角斗士的敌人
Always the enemy of a gladiator.
现在对我们来说却是朋友
Yet friend to us now.
主人给了我们在一起的理由
Domina has given excuse for us to be together.
让我们从不幸中获得了一丝幸运
Let us pluck blessing from misfortune.
Crixus 你还活着
Crixus, you live.
我的祷告应验了
My prayers, answered.
我应该多祷告一些
I would have more prayers,
好让我能够重回沙场
to return me to the sand to be by the men.
很快 你就可以回到你的兄弟们中间了
You shall rejoin your brothers soon enough.
兄弟们？
Brothers?
没有一个人来看过我
None have visited me.
甚至是Barca
Not even Barca.
你没有告诉他吗？
Have you not told him?
一直没有合适的时机
The moment has not arisen.
他在竞技场倒下了？
Has he fallen, in the arena?
正好相反
Far the opposite.
他赎回了他的自由
He has purchased his freedom.
那个迦太基野兽？
The Beast of Carthage?
如果Barca不做角斗士 他又能做什么？
What is Barca if not a gladiator?
人 自由漫步于这些高墙外的人
A man. Free to roam outside these walls.
这想法真奇特
The thought is foreign.
那个巨人去牧羊
The giant fuck tending goats
然后自己采摘蔬菜？
and picking vegetables?
与他宠爱的老婆Pietros在一起？
With Pietros his ever doting wife?
他没带那孩子走
He left the boy.
他迟早要和他的命根分家！
He'd sooner part with his own cock!
这个消息也让我很吃惊
The news found me surprised also.
他不想这样 但是别无选择
He did not wish it, but had no choice.
你跟他谈过？
You shared words with him?
没有 但是我从他的眼里看得出来
No, but I saw it in his eyes,
当他被人送出大门的时候
as he was escorted through the gates.
当时你在场？
You were there?
好好恢复体力
Regain your strength.
希望很快看见你手持利剑 重返训练场
I would see you with a sword in hand soon.
Barca走了
Barca gone.
斯巴达克斯成了战神
Spartacus champion.
我醒来后的世界已面目全非
I have awoken to a world of shit.
你拒绝Batiatus可真傻
You are a fool to refuse Batiatus.
他提出了很多不合理的要求
The man makes unreasonable demands.
他是你的主人
He is your master.
不管合理与否 他的命令就是你的职责
His demands your duty, unreasonable or otherwise.
我不会受迫去屠杀我的同胞
I will not be forced to slaughter my countrymen.
只不过衣服相同而已
Countrymen in dress only.
你和这些囚犯没有任何血缘关系
You share no kinship with these prisoners.
他们是杀人犯
They are murderers.
强奸犯
Rapists.
他们都该死
Their death well deserved.
那么 让另一个人去手刃他们吧
Then let another man's blade grant it.
你表现得 就像你在这件事上有选择权似的
You act as if you have free will in the matter.
你是一个角斗士
You are a gladiator.
我也是一个特雷斯人
I am a Thracian.
你只是一个奴隶
You are a slave.
越过这道高墙的下场
To cling to a life beyond these walls
就是看着自己肝脑涂地
is to see your heart parted from your chest.
你比任何人都清楚这一点
You above all others should know this.
我说话不经过考虑的
I do not think before I speak.
我得去找一个让我省心的同伴
I will remove myself to less deserving company.
Pietros 你…
Pietros…
是Gnaeus干的吗？
Gnaeus's hand?
你告诉我
I shall have a word.
又能怎么样呢？
To what end?
能换回Barca吗？
Will it see Barca return?
能换回我俩的重聚
Will it see us reunited,
还是主人承诺的自由？
or free, as he promised?
命运的强大 往往让人无可奈何
Fate often takes a man far from his heart.
我要让他后悔
To his regret.
剩下我一个人 在这思念心痛
Felt more keenly by the one left behind.
罗马人得知Theokoles
Rome is positively aflutter
战败的消息后 肯定震惊不已
with news of Theokoles' defeat.
没人接受得了 这样的事实
No one could believe such a thing was possible.
尤其是死在一个色雷斯人手里
Especially at the hands of a Thracian.
神明真是眷恋Batiatus家啊
The gods truly bless the House of Batiatus.
我们还打算和赞助人一起欢聚娱乐
We've even entertaining thoughts of a patron
来分享下我们的好运呢
to share in our good fortune.
嗯
Hm.
那你的好运 有没有往下延伸呢？
And does your good fortune extend downward?
我不明白你的意思
I don't follow.
女祭司啊
The Priestess.
生育仪式之后 你的肚子有动静了吗？
Has her fertility rite born any seed?
我没能在限期之内
I was unable to conclude the rite
与人结合
in the allotted time.
不是吧！
No!
真可惜 我丈夫不在
Well my husband was sadly absent.
另外那个人呢？
What of the other man?
哦 你还是没跟我讲 关于他的事情呢
Oh. You still have not told me anything about him.
是Solonius吗？
Is it Solonius?
我宁可跟条鳗鱼交媾
I would rather fuck an eel.
别 像你这么漂亮的女人 还是配得上一个男人的
No, no, a woman as beautiful as you are deserves a man.
是不是哪个位高权重的人…？
Someone of position maybe…?
他是个普普通通的人
He's no one of note.
普普通通的人…
No one of note…
是不是身体很强壮
Someone more physical, perhaps.
是奴隶吗？！
A slave?!
哦 你的杯子空了
Oh, your cups empty.
是不是啊？
Isn't it?
不能随便找个奴隶 太不合你身份了
But not just any slave, no not for you.
他得是天神亲自锻造出来的才行…
He would have to be forged by Jupiter himself…
我们换个话题吧
Let us move on from the subject.
好吧 换个话题
Of course. To other matters.
Crixus怎么样了？
How fares Crixus?
Crixus啊？
Crixus?
和Theokoles大战之后 他伤势如何啊
His injuries, suffered against Theokoles.
他还能活过来吗？
Is he expected to live?
体力算是恢复了
His strength returns.
真是好消息
Joyous news.
如此猛男就这样死掉
It would be a great tragedy to see such a man
岂不是太悲剧了？
pass from this world, would it not?
是啊
It would.
只可惜他不能参加Mercato的竞技了
Pity he will not take the sand in good Mercato's games.
我还想看他挥剑斩人呢
I long to see his sword thrust home.
结果怎么样？
How did you fare?
就是上次比赛的赌注
The game of dice and bones.
不好 跟我往常一样
Poorly, as I often have.
下次 我会补回损失的…
I will balance the loss at next chance…
Pietros好像不管他的鸟群了
It would seem Pietros has lost control of his flock.
Pietros啊…
Pietros…
傻孩子 自尽了
The boy has freed himself.
Gnaeus 我操你妈！
Gnaeus!
够了！
Enough!
这是为了什么？
What is this foolishness?
为了Pietros
Pietros.
他自尽了
The boy took his own life.
真可惜他…
He will be missed…
再也尝不到我的阳物了
Especially his lips around my cock.
今早我还鼓吹说 我有全卡普亚最好的持网和三叉戟角斗士！
This morning I boasted the top Retiarius in all of Capua!
现在我却只剩乱石堆上的
Now I possess nothing more than bones
断骨和迸溅的脑浆了！
and brains scattered upon the rocks!
对不起
Apologies.
去你妈的对不起！
Fuck your apologies!
失去的财富 我会全部收回来！
I will have return of the value lost!
死去角斗士的身价 要从你的奖金中扣
The price of the man will be subtracted from your winnings
直到补足为止！
until the remainder is balanced!
随您心意 主人
As you see fit, Dominus.
这都是为了什么？
All of this for what?
Pietros吗？
Pietros?
他算个鸟 贱货的杂种
He was nothing. Shit from a whore.
他是个人 他的性命也有价值
He was a man. His life had worth.
最多值半毛钱
Half a coin at most.
Gnaeus可是个角斗士！
Gnaeus was a gladiator!
成年累月的训练 每次提高都付出了昂贵的代价
Years of training, each mounting to exorbitant cost.
那才叫价值！
That is true worth!
他不配活着
He did not deserve to live.
只有我才能决定生死！
I alone decides who live!
不是你！你这该死的奴隶！
Not you! Not a fucking slave!
靠！
Argh!
我已经够宽宏大量了
My generosity has been boundless,
而你 直到现在还不服从我
yet you defy me still.
Mercato的竞技赛就要到了
Mercato's games are upon us.
我希望你能作为一个忠诚的罗马人去战斗
I expect you to fight as a loyal Roman.
或者 做个色雷斯人死去
Or die as a Thracian.
带他去看医生
See him to the Medicus.
你为这个孩子落泪？
You shed tears for the boy?
他的死让我心痛
His passing saddens me.
他这种弱者不适合这里
He was too weak for this place.
尤其在没有Barca保护他时
Without Barca to protect him.
并非每个人都是强者
Not all of us can be strong.
有没有言归于好？
Have you been making friends again?
Gnaeus啊
Gnaeus.
他不干
A disagreement.
然后你就为不值一提的Pietros当出头鸟
And you emerged the battered cunt.
不会吧 难道你还斗不过Gnaeus的小网么？
What, did his tiny net prove too fierce an opponent?
你可是杀死死亡之影的英雄啊？！
For the slayer of Theokoles?
你去问他自己好了
Ask the man himself.
但你要到悬崖下面去问他了
If you can scrape enough of him off the cliff for reply.
Gnaeus死了？
Gnaeus is dead?
你为什么要杀死他？
What reason did you have to take his life?
无可奉告
My reasoning lies forever silent.
你的行为背叛了我们所有人
Your actions betray us all.
Gnaeus是一位角头士！
Gnaeus was a gladiator!
是我们的兄弟
A brother.
他不是我的兄弟
He was no brother of mine.
在你宣誓之后
When you swore the oath,
这里的所有人 都变成你的兄弟了
every man in here became your brother,
值得你为他们 在竞技场上光荣地死去
deservide of an honorable death in the arena.
你的行为亵渎了我们曾经的并肩作战
Your actions shame my fighting beside you.
你说得好像你在这里有权选择似的
You speak as if you had choice in the matter.
我有 当时在角斗场上 我就选择
I did and I chose not to end your life
让你活了下来
in the arena.
但我现在真有些后悔
A decision I presently regret.
我也有些后悔
As do I.
你很了解Pietros？
You knew Pietros well?
我只是路过这里
Only in passing.
但你在照料他的宠物
Yet you tend to his pets.
而且是自觉自愿的
A duty not required.
我这人就这傻样
A foolish gesture.
你天性善良
Born of a kind heart.
我有些吃惊 Barca赎得自由后
It surprises, that Barca would claim his freedom
会抛弃心爱的人 独自离去
at yet leave the things he loved in captivity.
他是否跟你提起过
Did he speak to you of his plans
他离开训练场后的打算？
for life outside the Ludus?
没有
No.
他跟Ashur吵过架吗？
Did he exchange words with Ashur?
你说Ashur？
Ashur?
当时他有没有在场？
He was there, was he not?
我想不起来了
I do not recall.
我敢说 如果你认真想想的话 肯定记得…
Surely if you set your mind to the task…
对不起 我该回去了
Apologies, but I must return to the villa.
主人在等我呢
Domina awaits.
你的眼神有些慌乱 说明你在撒谎
The fear in your eyes betray the lie on your tongue.
你的问题会害死我的
Your questions put me in harm's way.
劳驾 让一下路
Please. Let me pass.
时间过得真快呀
The day approaches
终于可以摆脱这玩意了
when I'm finally free of this.
也许你可以把它改成不错的阳物啊
Perhaps you can fashion a proper cock from it.
都走吧
Remove yourselves.
你留下
Remain.
我问你点事
I seek information.
什么事？
On what subject?
关于Barca的事
Barca.
我知道他在Theokoles之战中下了赌注
I understand he made wager upon the Theokoles fight.
没错 还赢了一笔巨款
Yeah, and won a small fortune,
并用来赎回了自由
applied towards his freedom.
他怎么不带Pietros一起走？
With no thought towards Pietros?
钱不够赎回两个人的自由
Not enough coin remained to liberate him.
Barca当时眼泪汪汪的
Barca's eyes filled with tears,
尽管有些悔恨
though spurred by regret
但还是为自由动心了 我想是这样吧
or impending freedom, I know not.
看到奴役的枷锁被去掉 他很激动啊
It is a stirring sight to see the bonds of servitude lifted.
是的
Hm.
看着Barca离开别墅
I confess my eyes swimming
我的眼睛也湿润了
as Barca took leave of the villa.
还有谁看到Barca离开？
Who else offered farewells?
啊 只有主人和我两个
Ah, only our master and myself.
Naevia说 是她陪Barca走到门口的
Naevia claims to have escorted Barca to the gates.
她没说你也在场
She made no mention of your presents.
天哪 她那么天真 很容易…
Why, she's a simple thing, her mind easily…
这些矛盾的说法让我怀疑
Stories in conflict give me concern.
如果我发现
If I find there is more to the matter
Barca的离去有问题…
of Barca's departure…
我还会来找你的
we shall have words.
你还信仰他们？
You still believe in them?
信仰神？
The gods?
是的
Yes.
为什么？
Why?
我们整个村都被毁了
Our entire village is gone.
我们认识的人也都被杀害了
Everyone we knew, dead.
如果没有神佑…
If there are no gods…
我们就不可能活在世上…
there is nothing to shape what happens in our lives…
一切都会失去意义
There is no meaning to any of it.
如果没有神佑 我们怎会走到一起…
I cannot believe the gods would lead me to you…
我又怎会得到你如此的疼爱…
to bless me with such love…
却无法为你分担痛苦
only to make me bare witness to your suffering.
一切都是神佑
No.
你要走的道路 神早就给你设计好了
There is a deeper purpose to the path you've been set upon.
只不过你现在还没有发现这条路
One that has yet to reveal itself.
我再也不会让你离开我了
I will never see you from my side again.
没有你 我就没有了活着的理由
Without you, there is no reason for breath.
活着的理由永远存在
There is always reason to live.
但我可能会找不到
I would be lost.
不会的
No.
神会指引你走上正确的道路
The gods would set you on the proper path.
你只需闭上眼睛…
All you have to do is close your eyes…
把自己交到神的手中
and place yourself in their hands.
我们要出发了
We leave for the games.
你想好了吗？
Is your decision made?
想好了
It is.
这算是什么答案？
What sort of answer is this?
礼节而已
A gesture.
我不在乎给我这个有何意义
I care not for its means of delivery.
即使那意味着乐意服从
Perhaps its meaning will be more agreeable.
那就说说吧
Out with it, then.
Sura经常和我说起神明
Sura spoke often to me of the gods.
她相信神明
She believed in them.
我却从不相信
I never truly have.
你算什么 居然敢质疑神明！
The cock on you, daring to doubt the gods!
我已经受够痛苦了
And I have suffered much for it.
到此为止
But no longer.
从现在开始…
From this point forward…
我把自己奉献给她的信仰…
I give myself over to her beliefs…
接受我的命运
and embrace my fate.
你的话 让我非常喜悦
Your words give my heart great joy.
甚至让我不再想知道
Enough even to erase questions
为什么行政官儿子的剑
of how a blade belonging to the Magistrate's son
会在你手里
came to your possession.
让我们抛却过往吧
Let us put the past truly behind us.
来吧 比赛在等着你呢
Come the games await you.
但我有一个条件
I have but one condition.
条件？
Condition?
你拍我马屁 就是为了跟我提要求？
You kiss my cheek only to finger my ass?!
呃！说！
Uh! Speak!
在我割掉你该死的舌头前 快讲
Before I carve out your fucking tongue.
我会倾尽全力
I will take to the sands
去对抗我自己的同胞
against the spectre of my countrymen.
但我要独自一人面对
But I will face them alone.
六个对你一个？
Six to your one?
我不会让卡普亚的战神为这样的谬论冒险
I will not risk the Champion of Capua to such absurdity.
如果这是我的命运
If this is my fate,
如果这确实就是神明
if this is the path the gods
为我安排的路…
have truly set me upon…
那他们就不会让我失败的
then they will not see me fall.
如果你是错的呢？
And if you are wrong?
那我会在与妻子重聚之前
Then I will give your city
给你呈现一场精彩的…
a great spectacle of blood…
血光盛宴
before joining my wife.
神明已经帮你走了这么远
The gods have brought you this far.
我相信这还远未结束
I believe they are not done with you yet.
但是 我也有一个条件
But I have a condition of my own.
当你杀掉所有那些
When you have killed the last of these shits
假装成你同胞的人时
garbed as your countrymen,
你体内残存的色雷斯人性 就会和他们一起灭绝
what's left of the Thracian inside you dies with them
你要接受命运
and you will embrace this fate
去做命定的斯巴达克斯
and your destiny as Spartacus,
去做卡普亚的战神
the Champion of Capua.
卡普亚的市民们！
Citizens of Capua!
今天 我们很荣幸地
Today, we honor
请到了尊贵的Marcus Minucius Rufus
the noble Marcus Minucius Rufus.
罗马执政官和无比荣耀的指挥官
A Roman consul and commander unmatched in glory.
作为贺礼 Mercato将再现
As tribute, good Mercato has seen fit to re-enact
他祖父最著名的
his grandfather's most famous victory
击败色雷斯部落之战！
against the Thracian hordes!
看看站在你们面前的囚徒
Gaze at the prisoners standing before you.
想象一下色雷斯人梅迪部落 入侵马其顿省的情景
And imagine the Thracian Maedi that invaded Macedonia.
抢劫 掠夺我们高贵的人民
Rape, pillaging its noble people.
杀掉了所有的人…
Murdering all in their path…
甚至还杀了罗马地方官！
even a Roman governor!
暴行和疯狂弥漫着整块大地
Violence and madness swept the land.
仰望天庭
Echoing into the heavens,
那里的天神也不忍相看
where the gods themselves turned their backs.
似乎都迷失了 直到罗马人派出他所眷顾的宠子…
All seemed lost, until Rome dispatched it's favored son…
Marcus Minucius Rufus进场！
Enter Marcus Minucius Rufus!
要扮演可敬的Rufus
For the honorable role of Rufus,
只有一个人选
there was but one choice.
送雨的使者！
The Bringer of Rain!
屠灭死亡之影的勇士！
The Slayer of Theokoles!
卡普亚的战神…
The Champion of Capua…
站起来！
Stand up!
我将其送给你们
I present to you.
斯巴达克斯！！！
Spartacus!!!
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
我还以为我们尊敬的是你祖父
I thought it was your grandfather we honor.
原来人们赞誉的是「斯巴达克斯」啊
Yet the crowd chants "Spartacus".
不要为小事伤神 Mercato
Worry not of details, good Mercato.
荣耀是你祖父一个人的
The glory is your grandfather's alone.
来吧！
Come!
发信号 让光荣的胜利之战开始吧！
Give the signal to begin the glorious victory!
为表达对Marcus Minucius Rufus的敬意…
In honor of Marcus Minucius Rufus…
让血流成河吧！
Let blood be shed!
你所需要做的就是 闭上眼睛
All you have to do is close your eyes
把自己交到神明手中…
and place yourself in their hands…
啊！
Yeah!
你真认为 我祖父赢了此次战争吗？
You do realize my grandfather won this battle?
或许今天 历史不会重现了
Perhaps this day history will not repeat itself.
总有活下去的理由
There is always a reason to live.
神明会安排你走上正确的道路
The gods would set you on the proper path.
啊！
YEAH!
他战斗起来像着魔了一样
He fights like a man possessed.
被天神附体了
By the gods themselves.
杀！
Kill!
不要
Don't.
精彩的表演！
A marvelous show!
很荣幸为您服务
An honor to be of service.
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
我…
I…
就是…
AM…
斯巴达克斯！！！
Spartacus!!!
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!